Eat, my darling, eat so you'll get stronger.
I thought of Ma. She used to be so mad when I said I wasn’t hungry.
For her, that feeling was irrelevant. The idea of not eating by choice was impossible to comprehend. When there is food, you eat, you eat as much as you can.
Only then did I start to perceive how much of a blessed childhood I had.
I looked at the dry dunes ahead of me and tears came to my eyes. I missed my mother.
So I ate. I would make her proud.
I spent a week around that village.
There were other birds too. Cuckoos, warblers, nightjars. A bunch of tiny solo travellers, scared beyond belief.
We kept to ourselves but secretly, we looked at each other. Which ones would make it, we wondered.
We knew too well that many of us would never see the other side.
Yet, none of us turned back. We just ate. Ate, ate, ate.
There was enough food for all of us, so there was no need to fight.
The Sahel is a blessed oasis for travellers, the last stop before the unknown.
I ate and I grew. Within a week, I had doubled in size.
One morning, I flew to a pond to drink and I stared at my reflection in total disbelief.
“You look stunned.” An old chiffchaff was looking at me with a sarcastic face.
“Sorry. It’s just that I changed so much. I can’t recognise myself.”
“Well, get used to it. You’re a migrant now. You’ll have to change much more than this when you get to the other side.
Believe me, if you want to fit in, you will have to become someone else.
Migrants see too much to ever remain who they were before the journey.”
“But what if I don’t want to change?”
He laughed. “Identity is a shifting concept, young lady. Soon you’ll understand.”
I looked at the Sahara. The sun was setting, covering up the dunes with a golden blanket. So beautiful, charmingly calling us to our death.
But I wasn’t scared anymore. I was at peace. I was as ready as I could ever be.
So I took off and followed my calling.